<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Neat Systems Blog</title>
  <subtitle>Making your systems tidy? We just think that&#39;s neat!</subtitle>
  <link href="https://neatsystems.dev/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://neatsystems.dev/" />
  <updated>2025-08-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://neatsystems.dev/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Neat Systems</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Growth Challenges at VC Scale</title>
    <link href="https://neatsystems.dev/blog/vc-rounds-growth-challenges/" />
    <updated>2025-08-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://neatsystems.dev/blog/vc-rounds-growth-challenges/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Neat Systems believes that building a sustainable organization ready to thrive in times of rapid growth requires a holistic approach to business problems. The business problems and subject areas on which we focus are often separated from each other or thought of as disparate disciplines, including technical communication, marketing, and information security. By focusing on the flow of information through these interrelated systems, many seemingly-separate problems can be resolved by treating a shared root cause. Crucially, some of these root causes are natural and inherent aspects of achieving funders&#39; common goals for venture capital rounds. As such, they can&#39;t be prevented without also blocking growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use VC rounds to measure organization scale because most investors share certain objectives as outcomes for each stage of growth. Those objectives are often linked to types of organizational change that require shifts in information storage and communication patterns. They also correspond directly to the parts of process effectiveness most critical to streamline at each stage of growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-first-growth-point-seed-stage&quot;&gt;The First Growth Point: Seed Stage&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first growth inflection point is around a seed stage VC funding round, often around 10-15 employees. At this stage, especially for B2B SaaS, your CTO and other non-sales leaders often begin paying attention to the compliance and legal requirements for selling into larger organizations. You&#39;re working towards product-market fit, and you may have a not-just-founders team now. You&#39;re possibly starting to look into SOC 2 or similar to unlock access to enterprise clients. Depending on how heavily-regulated your industry is, compliance requirements may shift at any stage of the organization&#39;s development. Across all sectors, though, this tends to be the first time that your organization encounters an externally-driven need to have documentation around certain subjects. The external pressure often results in an organization developing documentation that does not align to actual processes or policies as used in people&#39;s daily work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Misaligned documentation that does not reflect the organization&#39;s actual culture creates cultural drift. New hires can&#39;t tell the difference between documentation created for actual reference, aspirational documentation of processes the organization wishes it had, and documentation you felt obligated to write but which nobody actually uses. Also, as your organization reaches this stage of growth, executives tend to be less hands-on as you begin to have employees doing more of the day-to-day building, selling, and fixing of the product or service. This makes spotting undesired working practices harder than when the founders were in every meeting, able to easily keep track of process because they were directly involved in every project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These changes all lead to inconveniences and roadblocks that employees often perceive as scattered problems, but that really point at a shift in the organization: away from a unified way of viewing the world and handling tasks, towards specialization of people and processes. This is an important sign that you&#39;re starting to grow! The organization is no longer one or two people, but its own being. Dealing with process discrepancies sooner lets you better optimize productivity and achieve a healthy, working relationship with less of the frustration that comes from learning that a teammate has not been using the process you intended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 10 to 15 people is often where people first start to notice that they have a knowledge management issue, because here or at some point soon, you can no longer just read every Slack channel or be in all of the meetings and know what&#39;s going on. You have to begin organizing conscious forms of communication. In a remote or remote-first environment, this may even include conscious organization of informal communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;series-a&quot;&gt;Series A&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next inflection point is around the time of a Series A round. This is often around 40-50 employees, but I&#39;ve seen it happen as small as 35 and some organizations make it pretty close to 80 employees before hitting this phase&#39;s challenges. You feel like your offering is actually solving a problem for clients, and your market is full of potential. You&#39;re doubling the size of your team while staying scrappy. You might also be thinking more seriously about compliance certifications to ease the burden of vendor security questionnaires from your prospects and clients, though it&#39;s just as common to start feeling that pain closer to Series B. At this size, one universal knowledge management system with flat organization/access is no longer sufficient. You have to break things down into chunks for different roles and goals supporting the organization&#39;s mission. Even if the information is well organized, it&#39;s still too much information, even with a summary, for one person to keep track of as an individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fully-colocated organizations, this is a scale where you likely need to develop systems for recording what happens in meetings. Remote or multi-office organizations may get away with just recordings/transcriptions of calls, but colocated teams will need to create process to ensure minutes and action items are recorded from in-person meetings. Decisions and decision-making history (including discussions and reasons for outcomes) at this stage will form the core of your organization&#39;s future culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;series-b&quot;&gt;Series B&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third inflection point is around your Series B round, typically 80-100 employees. Around 80 to 100 is where you start to have those really specialized teams forming. At earlier stages, employees may have been invested in every high-priority project regardless of team, but at this stage that&#39;s not sustainable. At Series B, you have people who don&#39;t need a summary of what&#39;s in progress with high-priority projects, but do need to know the outcome of recently-completed projects or stages. You must shift from making organizational information &lt;em&gt;digestible&lt;/em&gt; to making the information &lt;em&gt;actionable&lt;/em&gt; for a diverse range of users throughout the organization. As part of that shift, remote or remote-first organizations likely need to focus on processes for recording concrete action items in a way they may have gotten away with not doing before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colocated organizations are more likely to start thinking about adding additional locations/offices at this stage, and should think about risks and benefits of expansion. If you do plan to expand from fully-colocated to multi-location, beginning to incorporate processes and systems that will support multiple locations at this stage as possible can enable better change management. Even if you stay in one location, at this size you won&#39;t run into everyone accidentally on a regular basis any more, because the office is getting too big! Creating opportunities for employees to have those encounters will be critical to maintaining the benefits of colocation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;series-c&quot;&gt;Series C&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final inflection point we&#39;ll discuss here is around a Series C round, typically 250-300 people but up to 500 in some cases. As you exceed 200 employees and continue growing, your organization becomes even more diverse in terms of skill set, and teams further specialize. You begin to need people to take action who have no grounding in the specialty for which the action is required. For example, security might need something really specific from the sales team or vice versa. The rapidly-growing number and criticality of these requests create a serious and urgent need to improve cross-functional communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This scale is typically out of scope for Neat Systems. At this size, organizations really stand to benefit from having one or more full-time operations and information security specialists looking at how the organization stores and processes information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether your organization is just starting to contemplate a seed or feeling nearly ready for your C, organizing your business to support your funders&#39; goals is critical to your ability to scale and achieve the founders&#39; mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;d like to learn more about how Neat Systems can help your organization, email Margaret@ this domain or &lt;a href=&quot;https://calendar.google.com/calendar/u/0/appointments/schedules/AcZssZ0l8wwk__O7t1icTZ5MJU7S4b7yssXide30lGwA6RTmj93ztrt_VAcdRk2HslCtcOI5K_zWTg4L&quot;&gt;book a call&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;acknowledgements&quot;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to Wes Wheless of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.developmyip.com/&quot;&gt;Develop My IP&lt;/a&gt;, with whom I discussed this concept before forming the organization and whose guidance was extremely helpful in identifying why I think of seemingly-disparate problems as symptoms of a shared root cause.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hello, World!</title>
    <link href="https://neatsystems.dev/blog/hello-world/" />
    <updated>2025-02-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://neatsystems.dev/blog/hello-world/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the first post on the new blog of the new website of the new company, Neat Systems! The name comes from a combination of two origins:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Neat&amp;quot; as in Tidy, because we hope to help organizations undergoing periods of rapid growth ensure that communication and organization systems are set up to enable, rather than interfere with employees. At several key inflection points, the effectiveness of internal communications (and the ripple effect that has on external communications) can really make or break the employee experience, and in some cases even the organization&#39;s ability to accomplish your mission. Neat Systems strives to help you find the patterns that work and strip away the ones that don&#39;t, so your effort goes to changing the world instead of changing between tabs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Neat&amp;quot; as in Cool, because we just think it&#39;s neat! We don&#39;t believe there is any one-size-fits-all approach to communicating, especially in rapidly growing businesses. No two hockey sticks are exactly alike. We want to learn about your organization&#39;s unique approach and advantages, so effective communication feels natural rather than restrictive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plenty more information about our approach, our offerings, and our work so far will be coming soon. For now, welcome to Neat Systems!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>